A Guide to the Correspondence and Supporting Documentation of the Executive Office of Governor Robert F. McDonnell, 2010-2013 (bulk 2010-2011).
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Executive Office Correspondence of Governor Robert F. McDonnell,
2010-2013 (bulk 2010-2011).
The Library of Virginia
51146
Virginia. Governor (2010-2014: McDonnell).
1.05 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8 Types of sealed information may include, but are not limited to: medical records, personnel records, and attorney-client communications. Restricted records in this collection have been sealed but not removed from the collection.
The Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia, 2.2-3705.5) and the Virginia Health Records Privacy Act (Code of Virginia, 32.1-172.1:03) establish guidelines for restricting access to medical and other confidential forms of information in order to protect personal privacy. Protected health information (PHI) as defined under the Privacy Regulations issued under the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) includes, but is not limited to, personally identifiable information such as names, addresses, and social security numbers. The Virginia Public Records Act (Code of Virginia, 42.1-78) includes a provision for closing all privacy protected information for 75 years from the date of creation.
Acquisition Information
Office of the Governor, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219, accession 51146 transferred on 9 January 2014.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Executive Office is a division of the Office of the Governor in the Executive Branch of Virginia state government. Members of the Executive Office include the Governor, Chief of Staff, Counselor to the Governor and their assistants. The Chief of Staff is the chief operating officer of state government, responsible for all aspects of service to citizens. The Chief oversees the Cabinet members and agency heads in the administration of state government and is also responsible for the operations of the Governor's Office and is assisted in these responsibilities by a Deputy Chief of Staff.
Robert F. McDonnell was elected 71st governor of the Commonwealth of Virginia in November 2009 and inaugurated on 16 January 2010. He served until 11 January 2014.
Scope and Content
The Correspondence and Supporting Documentation of Governor McDonnell's Executive office are house in 3 boxes. The bulk of the collection consists of printed emails and supporting documentation of said internal email communications. These records concern various events and activities of the Governor and his office during his administration including. All three series include correspondence, both internally between the governor and staff, and externally with constituents, politicians and stake holders.
The series arrangement reflects the Correspondence and Communications work flow of the McDonnell Executive office. Some of the supporting documentation includes Governor's public schedule, recommendation letters, sympathies, media advisories / press releases, newspaper clippings / news summaries, publications featuring the Governor and briefing papers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series, and chronologically within:
Series I. Correspondence, 2010-2011
Series II. Action Items, 2010-2012
Series III. Status Reports, 2010-2011
Related Material
The Governor Robert F. McDonnell Administration Web Archive Collection, 2010-2014 contains archived versions of websites for the Governor's Office, his initiative sites, and the sites of his cabinet secretaries. Also included are the related sites for the First Lady (Maureen McDonnell), as well as the Lt. Governor (Bill Bolling), and Attorney General (Ken Cuccinelli).
The Constituent Correspondence of Governor Robert F. McDonnell Collection
The Records of Robert F. McDonnell's Deputy Chief of Staff Matt Conrad Collection
The Records of the Executive Mansion of Governor Robert F. McDonnell Collection
The Records of Governor Robert F. McDonnell's Secretary of Transportation Collection
The Records of Governor Robert F. McDonnell's Secretary of Administration Collection
Contents List
- I. Correspondence, 2010-2011.
  Correspondence to dignitaries and politicians, internal staff, stake holders, and constituents from the first two years of Governor McDonnell's term comprises this series. This includes both email correspondence that has been printed from his inbox, and correspondence written on letterhead. The types of content in this series include congratulations, sympathies, recommendations, opinions on budgets and legislation, and gratitude to name a few.Unlike McDonnell's Constituent Correspondence collection (Accession 51119) which is primarily incoming mail, the majority of the communication here is outgoing, whether to constituents, internal staff, or VIPs.
  - Correspondence 2010 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (1 of 2) 2010 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2) 2010 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 2010 Mar. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence 2010 Apr. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 2010 May. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 2010 June. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence 2010 July. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence 2010 Aug-Sept. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence 2010 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence 2010 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence 2010 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence 2011 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence 2011 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (1 of 2) 2011 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2) 2011 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence 2011 Mar. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 2011 Apr-May. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 2011 June-July. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 2011 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence 2011 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 2011 Oct-Dec. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- II. Action Items, 2010-2013.
  The Action Items series differs from the first series of Correspondence and related material in that the records mostly include hand written annotations to the internal staff from Governor McDonnell. The content of the correspondence tend to focus on actions to be taken by he and his staff on various clerical, administrative, and legislative matters.. The bulk of Governor McDonnell's annotations are directed at Administrative Assistant Pam Watts, and a significant portion are also directed at and concern Virginia's First Secretary of Veteran Affairs and Homeland Security, Terrie Suit. One of the recurring topics in this series is Medicaid Expansion.
  - Action Items 2010 May-Aug. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Action Items 2010 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Action Items 2010 Oct-Nov. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Action Items (1 of 2) 2010 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Action Items (2 of 2) 2010 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Action Items 2011 Jan. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Action Items 2011 Feb. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Action Items 2011 Mar-Dec. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Action Items 2012 July-Dec. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Action Items 2013 Jan-Sept. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- III. Status Reports, 2010-2011 DATES.
  This third series of Correspondence is very similar to the second series, Action items in that they include annotations for actions to be taken on specific matters covered in the correspondence. The correspondence and supporting documents in this series however, include a cover sheet outlining a very specific work flow titled, "Status Reports" which helped track the status of actions.
  - Status Reports 2010. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Status Reports 2011 Jan-May. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Status Reports 2011 May. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Status Reports 2011 June-Oct. (Box 3, Folder 9)